Mohammad Vatandoost Silab

Software Engineer

Cell: +98-937-1869568 Email: mohamadvatandoost512@gmail.com
Date of birth: 19/08/1995 Location: Tehran, Iran Github Page

Summary

I have more than 6 years of experience in Embedded, Desktop, and Back-End Software development for small and medium enterprises. I participate in all phases of the software development life cycle. I mainly work with C/C++, Qt framework, Golang, and Python. Most of my working experience is in a team, I enjoy helping my team to solve problems.

Experience

Software Engineer

Aug 2020 - present

Fanap-infra.ir

Fannap-infra is developing multiple Software projects. I am working in Behnama projects team. Behnama is a distributed video surveillance software (like Genetec) that manage more than 10000 cameras in more than 300 servers. It is built on micro-service architecture.

- Architecting streaming services(RTSP, Analyzer, Recording and WebRTC services) by using GRPC, Go, C++, Python and Kafka
- Stream Enrichment: Push Analyzer service output as Metadata to Kafka
- Writing a WebRTC player backend for playing live and records. It receives commands and sends records list and metadata by WebRTC data channel Go
- Developing Recording service for recording and playback streams Go
- Using GRPC for communication between services Go, C++ and Python
- Receiving RTSP(IP Camera stream) by FFmpeg library C/C++
- Developing Transcoding service for converting and exporting media by FFmpeg C/C++
- Creating recording file structure for minimizing head movement of HDD Go
- Adding motion detection (by OpenCV) to analyzer service Python
- Using Redis as notification service Go and C++
- Dockerise Stream and RTSP services
- Adding functional and integration tests by Postman

Software Engineer

3ddreams.ir

Dec 2019 – Jul 2020 (8 months)

3DDreams build the industry 3D printer devices with 4K resolution and 50 micro-meter layer thickness. I developed server and client software for the device. The server software is running in a raspberry pi inside the device and the client software is a cross platform app that run in a desktop computer.

- Building a CRUD for data by using QAbstractListModel and SQLite C++
- Convert SLC file to SVG, and render it in real-time for showing in UV projector
- Adding unit test by GTest and GMock to client and server project C++

- Implementing UI of the client application by QML
- Socket programming and using Protobuf for messages structure C++
- Using Serial Port for Communication with actuator C++.
- Using signal-slot pattern for multi-threading communication C++
- Using Jenkins for CI/CD

Embedded Software Engineer

raiwan.ir

Nov 2017 – OCT 2019 (2 years)

Raiwan works on designing and building IoT and industrial manufacturing and laboratory devices. I developed software for industrial devices. I designed and implemented algorithms for different use cases, such as: Oil industry, IoT, Polymer industry and civil industry.

- Receiving data from Socket at rate 96 MBit, then simultaneously Decode, Decrypt(Cryptopp library) and Mux(ffmpeg library) H.264 and audio(PCM to AAC) frames to MP4 – C/C++
- Writing a Linux USB Driver C
- Working with RS485 mode bus protocol in industrial devices C++
- Developing Android app that connect to modules by BLE and OTG, It receives files and send user commands Java
- Writing bitcoin mining farm monitoring software Node js and C

FreeLancer

Feb 2016 – Sep 2017 (1 year and 8 months)

I worked with multiple startups to build theirs MVP products.

- Receiving sensors data in real time from serial port and plot them by QtChart C++
- PID controller design for controlling temperature
- Preprocessing data by FFT and filters like Butterworth and averaging data chunk.
- Converting Matlab code of costumers to C++ code.
- Using UART and I2C protocol in Orange pi and Raspberry pi.
- Designing relational data base.
- Crawling websites with Selenium Java
- Building Nurse pager with ESP8266 (Arduino firmware)

Student Researcher

KNTU Aras robotic Lab

Nov 2014 – Jan 2016 (1 year and 3 months)

KNTU Aras robotic Lab research on UGV and MAV. I designed and programmed robot's embedded system.

• ARM Microcontroller(Stm32 series) and AVR programming (Used I2C, UART, SPI, PWM, USB and ADC peripherals).

- PCB Designing of Embedded systems.
- Working with Different sensors and Electronics modules.

Education

- University of Tehran, MS, Computer Software Engineering, (2019 2021) (GPA: 3.5/4)
- K. N. Toosi University of Technology, BS, Electronic Engineering, (2013 2018) (GPA: 3.3/4)

Recent Projects

- **fsEngine** Go <u>link</u>

A write-optimized object storage, designed for high load on commodity hardware.

- **Onvif** Go <u>link</u>

Onvif is an implementation of ONVIF protocol for managing onvif IP devices.

- **RTSPToKafka** C++ link

A service for streaming RTSP to Kafka topic.

- **Qt-Sample-App** C++ <u>link</u> Qt-Quick app sample.

AWARDS

- AUT cup 2016

Our Team achieved the second place in Rescue robots competition.

- IRAN Open 2015 robotic competition

Our Team achieved the first place in finding land mine robots competition.

- Chess Competition

I achieved the first place in chess competition between high schools students

Teaching

- Teaching Embedded software development course in Robotic lab of K. N. Toosi University of Technology
- Teacher assistant of Computer Network and Performance Evaluation of Computer Systems courses

Skills

- Languages: C, C++, Golang, Python, Bash, javascript and Java
- **Tools and Frameworks**: Qt, CMake, Message Queue (Kafka), Jenkins, Git, Docker, Matlab, GNS3, Keil and STM32Cube
- Protocols: GRPC, RTSP, WebRTC, Onvif, TCP, UDP, RS485 mode bus, RS232, I2C, UART and SPI
- Data Bases: Sqlite, Influxdb, PostgresSQL and MongoDB
- Tests: Unit tests, Functional tests, Integration tests, GTest and GMock
- Devices: Raspberry pi, Orange pi, Nano pi, STM32(ARM Cortex-M), Odroid and ESP8266
- **Other**: OOP, Functional Programming, Multithreading, QML, FFmpeg, Linux, Protobuf, Linux Module development, Pair programming, STL, Arduino, Agile (including Scrum/Kanban), REST, H264 and Jira